

West Lafavette. Indiana

Summary.

Software engineer with experience in building high performance large-scale network systems, honed at Meta. Through my PhD journey, I have developed measurement-based network systems to optimize video delivery, traditional and 360 videos. My work on video streaming and data center traffic has contributed to multiple publications that appeared in top venues

Professional Experience

Meta Platforms (FKA Facebook)

Menlo Park, CA

RESEARCH SCIENTIST

Aug. 2021 - Jul. 2022

- Conducted first large-scale characterization of traffic burstiness, contention, and loss
- · Shed important insights on the design of many different algorithms including buffer sharing, congestion control, and service placement algo-

Meta Platforms (FKA Facebook)

Menlo Park, CA

Ph.D. Software Engineer Intern

May 2021 - Aug. 2021

- Validated and enabled synchronized data collection at time scales as low as 100μ
- · Diagnosed firmware bugs and large congestion events through measurements over multiple data centers

Facebook Menlo Park CA

SOFTWARE ENGINEER Nov. 2020 - Apr. 2021

- · Developed highly efficient large-scale system to profile data centers network traffic in order of minutes
- Characterized traffic burstiness, and its impact on congestion and packet loss
- Created a production impact through tuning TCP window to diminish loss in data centers

Facebook Menlo Park, CA

Ph.D. Software Engineer Intern

Jun. 2020 - Aug. 2020

- · Applied state of the art algorithms to detect traffic bursts and atypical network events in data centers
- Uncovered a NIC firmware bug which causes packet loss even at low link utilization

Education

Purdue University

Ph.D. IN ELECTRICAL AND COMPUTER ENGINEERING

Aug. 2017 - Oct. 2023 (expected)

JUST(Jordan University of Science and Technology)

B.Sc. IN COMPUTER ENGINEERING

Sep. 2010 - Aug. 2015

Uppsala University

EXCHANGE STUDENT AT DEPARTMENT OF INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY

Aug. 2014 - Jan. 2015

Publications

- 1. "Dragonfly: Higher Perceptual Quality For Continuous 360" Video Playback." Ehab Ghabashneh, Chandan Bothra, Ramesh Govindan, Antonio Ortega, and Sanjay Rao. In Proceedings of ACM SIGCOMM, September 2023 (Acceptance Rate: 22%)
- 2. "A microscopic view of bursts, buffer contention, and loss in data centers." Ehab Ghabashneh, Yimeng Zhao, Cristian Lumezanu, Neil Spring, Srikanth Sundaresan, and Sanjay Rao. In Proceedings of ACM IMC, October 2022 (Acceptance rate: 26.4%)
- 3. "Xatu: Richer Neural Network Based Prediction for Video Streaming." Yun Seong Nam, Jianfei Gao, Chandan Bothra, Ehab Ghabashneh, Sanjay Rao, Bruno Ribeiro, Jibin Zhan, and Hui Zhang. In Proceedings of ACM SIGMETRICS, June 2022 (Acceptance rate: 19.5%)
- 4. "Exploring the interplay between CDN caching and video streaming performance." Ehab Ghabashneh and S Rao. In Proceedings of IEEE INFO-COM, July 2020 (Acceptance rate: 19.8%)

Research Experience _____

OCTOBER 4, 2023 E.GHABASHNEH

Interactive 360 Video Streaming

West Lafayette, IN Jul. 2020 - Present

ADVISORS: SANJAY RAO, ANTONIO ORTEGA, AND RAMESH GOVINDAN

Designed and built Dragonfly, a 360° video streaming system focusing on interactive continuous playback

- Evaluated Dragonfly over 100's of users trajectories, bandwidth traces, and videos.
- Improved the video quality by 1-3X over the state-of-the-art, and reduced the re-buffering events by 96%
- · Deployed Dragonfly on Meta Quest, and directed a user study with 30 participants. Users rated 70% of Dragonfly sessions as excellent in comparison to only 20% for state-of-the-art systems with the same rating

Characterize Data Center Traffic At Fine Time Scales

West Lafayette, IN

ADVISOR: SANJAY RAO AND SRIKANTH SUNDARESAN

June. 2020 - Oct. 2022

- Built large-scale infrastructure to characterize traffic data across all Meta hosts.
- Conducted the first large-scale joint analysis of traffic burstiness, contention, and loss
- · Induced multiple production impacts inside Meta, and provided insights to guide the design of many data center algorithms

CDN Caching and Video Streaming Performance

ADVISOR: SANJAY RAO June. 2018 - Aug. 2020

- Automated conducting measurement studies by streaming videos from multiple video publishers
- Introduced a new design point of exposing CDN information to adaptive bit-rate (ABR) algorithm
- Evaluated modified version of MPC (i.e. well-known ABR algorithm). Results showed that 91.5% of sessions had higher QoE, and throughput prediction error was cut-down for 81.7% of sessions

Honors & Awards

2022	Bilsland Dissertation Fellowship	Purdue University
2015	Presidential honor list (5 times) and Dean honor list (7 times)	JUST
2015	IAESTE summer internship program	IAESTE-Spain
2014	Dunia Beam scholarship	European Union
2010	Undergraduate scholarship	Jordan Ministry of Education

OCTOBER 4, 2023 E.GHABASHNEH